Guide to the Baruch Nadel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Baruch Nadel papers
1847-1992
1971-1985
MS 1393
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
(12 boxes)
The papers consist of Baruch Nadel's research materials for a proposed book on Abraham Stern, the founder of Lohamei Herut Israel ("Lehi"), an armed underground organization in British Palestine. The papers include more than 150 transcribed interviews conducted by Nadel, interviews by others with members of Lehi, memoirs by Lehi members and Stern aides, and poems and letters by Stern. Also included in the papers are Nadel's research materials concerning the emigration of Jews from Iraq between 1950 and 1951 and collected materials relating to Jewish life in Europe and to Nadel's father, MenahÌ£em Nadel, and others involved in early Zionist political groups, Palestine under the Mandate, and the State of Israel.
Nadel, Barukh
Related Materials
Audio cassettes of Nadel's interviews with Hillel Kook are in the Historical Sound Recordings Collection in the Yale University Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Baruch Nadel, 1984-1988 and 1991-1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Series II was opened to research in 2014; prior to that it was restricted under a donor-imposed access restriction.
Researchers are required to use the microfilm edition of the papers, call number HM208, except for Box 9 and the additions which were not filmed.
Existence and Location of Copies
The papers (excluding Box 9 and the additions) are also available on microfilm (8 reels, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM208.
Biographical / Historical
Baruch Nadel was born in Palestine on February 10, 1926. He was a member of the Haganah from 1942 to 1947, studied mathematics at the Hebrew University from 1945 to 1947, and joined the Lohamei Herut Israel ("Lehi") in 1948. Nadel served with the Israeli Defense Forces from 1951 to 1953. From 1957 to 1967 he was the manager of Nadel Advertising and in 1968 he joined the staff of the newspaper Yediot Aharonot. He is the author of books on Israeli history and politics.
Scope and Contents
The Baruch Nadel Papers consist of research materials collected by Nadel for use in his proposed studies of Abraham Stern and of the mass emigration of Jews from Iraq to Israel in 1950 and 1951. The papers also include correspondence, writings, printed material, and other documents pertaining to Baruch Nadel's father, Menahem Nadel, the Labor Zionist movement, and Israeli history. The bulk of the material is composed of interviews and documents relating to Abraham Stern, the founder of Lohamei Herut Israel ('Lehi'), an armed underground organization founded in 1940 which directed its activities against the British Mandatory authorities in Palestine. Though the papers include printed books, pamphlets, newspapers, and other materials dating from 1918 on, the bulk of the papers date after 1969. Series I, Abraham Stern files, is the largest of the three series.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series: I. Abraham Stern Files, 1929-1985. II. Iraqi Jewish Immigration Files, 1949-1985. III. Other Papers, 1918-1985, and two additions.
Jews -- History -- 1789-1945; Jews -- History -- 1945-; Jews; Labor Zionism -- Israel; World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground movements -- Palestine; Zionism; Great Britain -- Foreign relations -- Israel; Israel -- History; Palestine -- History -- 1917-1948; Interviews; Memoirs; Poetry; Songs; Journalists; Kook, Hillel, 1915-2001; Nadel, Barukh; Nadel, Menaḥem; Stern, Abraham, 1907-1942; Zamir, Roni; Israel. Tseva haganah le-Yiśraʼel; Haganah (Organization); Irgun tsevaʼi leʼumi; Jewish Agency for Palestine; Loḥame ḥerut Yiśraʼel
- Abraham Stern files, 1929-1984; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Nadel joined 'Lehi' in 1948 and began collecting documents about its history at that time. In 1970 Nadel decided to write a book about Stern and began a concentrated effort to collect materials and to interview persons concerning Stern, Lehi, and other underground resistance to British control of Palestine in the 1940s. Series I is composed of these materials, which Nadel gave to the Library in 1984 and 1985 and which have been left in the order established by Nadel.
  Series I begins with the testimonies of about 165 people interviewed by Nadel, either in person or by telephone. In most cases the interviewees reviewed and corrected Nadel's transcriptions of their interviews. Folders 1-24 contain these transcriptions as well as other materials gathered about the interviewee. Throughout the series Nadel has interspersed explanatory notes in Hebrew. Interview files are arranged and listed by personal name; however, not all materials by or about a person are in the same folder. For example, Nadel's interview with Stern's wife Rony Borshtien-Zamir is in folder 3, but an interview with Rony Stern made by Israeli television is in folder 13. The listing gives both the Hebrew description and an English translation along with a romanization of the Hebrew names based on standard Library of Congress cataloging practice. This spelling of names in roman characters may vary from spellings used in other sources. For instance, though Nadel refers in his notes to Hillel Kook, the listing gives his name as Hillel Ḳuḳ. Folders 25-28 contain several published volumes of memoirs of other underground members and two books of poems and songs by Stern. The volumes include short notes by Nadel. The contents of boxes 1-3 were donated in 1984. (Three audio cassettes of Nadel's interviews with Hillel Kook are in the Historical Sound Recordings Collection.)
  Boxes 4 and 5 are composed of more than 500 additional documents concerning Stern, which Nadel added to the papers in 1985. These documents include copies of Stern's letters, articles and poems by him, letters from people interviewed by Nadel, clippings, pamphlets, and photographs, and additional interviews and books. Nadel gave an arbitrary number to each document so as to be able to identify them in the explanations he wrote. These explanations are in folder 29 and serve as an inventory to the contents of boxes 4 and 5.
  Arrangement
  Boxes 1-3 contain materials arranged by record type. Materials in boxes 4 and 5 are arranged in numerical order.
  - Zarʿony, Benyamin, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - ben-Dav, Barukh, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Ḥantsʼinsḳy, Ṭobiah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - ʾAldad, Dr. Yisraʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - ʾElaʿzer, Z'uly, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Daviny, Ḥayyim, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Smoler, Shalom, letter, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Grushḳin, Miriam, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Aʾiyzner, Zaʾev, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Z'rez'evsḳy, Yitshak, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Minḳovits, Gershon, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
  - Aʿdoyot, Keṭaʿi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳuḳ, Hillel, notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Yelin-Mov, notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Yaʾir songbooks, notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - ʾOrnsṭien, Yẚkov, notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Kuk's congregation of Israel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Army (Nahal), notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Gabi and Haniah Tselts'insky, affidavit, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Affidavit, note, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Banaʿi, Yaʾkov, memoirs, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Banaʿi memoirs, notes, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Note to the book of Daṿid Ha-Cohen, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Research summary, Hebrew, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Research summary, English, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
  - Borshṭien-Zamir, Rony, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
  - Broshi, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Shmuʾelevits', Maty, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Masary, Daniʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
  - Habanshtriet, Ḳalerah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Kremer, Moniah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - ben-Eʾlisar, Eʾliahu, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Krol, Aʾlekhsander, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Ṿienshel, Dr. Yaʿkov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Cohen (Coen), Renaʾto, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Fienstien, Dr. Rʾuven, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Mikhlin, Tobiah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - ben-Yosef, Mikhaʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Brener, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Aʾpelbaim, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Thomi, Abraham, letter, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Rabinovits, Hanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - ʾUr, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Yaʿḳovy, Dr. Yaʿḳov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳuperniḳ, Yokherd, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Tahon, Yehudit, letter, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Yaʿkobi (Borstein), Raḥel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
  - Śarah and Ḥayot (Man), memoirs, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Ḥayotman, Yehudah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Merlin, Shmuʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Mosaʾief- Aliʾev, Ḥanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Shvitser-Raziʾel, Shoshanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Shvitser-Tsimerman, Yonah and Shoshanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Shapiraʾ-Raʾovny, Ḥaisiah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Re⊽iḳovits-Shamir, Hadasah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Svoraʾi, Masha and Ṭova, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Roṭshṭien, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Tselniḳ (for Dr. Ṿienshel), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Dg'oʾn, Dr. (for Ṿienshel), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Shṿoʾarts, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - ʾUr, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6, Reel 1U)
  - Robinson, Professor Pinḥas, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Sṭerlits, Mordikhai, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 7, Reel 1U)
  - Yaʿḳovi, Shlomah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Moldavsḳy, Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Raʾovny, Nasim, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8, Reel 1U)
  - Pozner, Shlomah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Ordy, Miriam, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Segal, HaRev (and Shlomah Yaʿḳovi), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Goṭḳovsḳy, Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳuḳ, Hilel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳoversḳy, Ḥayyim, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Siṭon, Daṿid, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Grinberg, ʾUri Tsvi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Hadasi, Tsvi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Laḥover, Professor Daṿid, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Gepner, Benyamin, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
  - Rabid, ʾEliahu and Miriam, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳahaʾn, Maʾir, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Aʾlṭman, Dr. Aʾriah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Kohen, Benyamin, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Behiri, Nataniʾel and Hayah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Selman, ʾAvrasha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Serebro, Masha and Natsḥiah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - ʾErlikh, ʾAvner, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
  - Lankin, ʾEliahu, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Raziʾel, Shoshanah (about ʾIlin), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Shniʾorson, Yehuda Liv, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Boḳsboim, Yosef, letter, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - ʾAharonovits, ʾAhova, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - (About) Mateniah, ʾEliʿazer, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Maten, Dr. ʾEliʿazer, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳonlovsḳy, Raḥel, postcards, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Yaʾir to H. Sh. HaLeṿi, postcards, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - 3 postcards from Yaʾir to Ḥanah Dimenṭ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Rozenṭal, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Marḳ-Daviri, Raḥel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳlets'ḳin, Rafaʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Yafah, Yemimah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Dimeʾnt-Ṿiderman, Ḥanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - ʾAvermansḳy, Yaʿkov Daṿid, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
  - Safir, Pinḥas, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Ṿulman, Professor Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Leṿin, Dr. Daniʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Yiśraʾeli, Yehoshuʿa (cattle), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Grinberg, Dr. Shmuʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Yeruselami, Dr. Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - ʾAsher, Hanas, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Ṭanenbaʾum, Herman, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Raṭosh and Perlman, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Shmuʾelvits and Siḳaʾ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Ḳorfu, Ḥayyim, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - ʾElrʾai, Yehudah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Langsfelder, Neli, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - Taboʾah, Yiśraʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
  - "Hayyim Shekʾalah" by Rony Śṭern, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 13, Reel 2U)
  - Memoirs of ʾAriah Ḳotser on Yaʾir, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14, Reel 2U)
  - ʾOrnen, ʿUzi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Ginian-Leṿin, Śarah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - (About) Zeligman, Maḳs, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Ben-Tsion and Rabin, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Friman, Dudiḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Gipny, Śergaʾ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳamelhar, Tsvi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Morz'insḳy, ʾEsther and Mordikhi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Shits, Rut, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Yelin, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Yeshonsḳy, Saniah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳoṭiḳ, Yaʿḳov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 15, Reel 2U)
  - Nagavy, Shabataʾy, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Yelin-Mor, Natan, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Nadel, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Kayyits, ʿEmanuʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Shluger, Yehudit, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Shluger, Engineer about Rony, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Ben-Daṿid, ʾEster (Dimenṭ), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - ʿEvri-Goṭḳovsḳy, Nivṭah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Yaron, Yerhamiʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Ḥason, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Shapaḳ, ʾEliahu, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Goṿezah, Dr. Vorah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 16, Reel 2U)
  - Tselniḳ, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17, Reel 2U)
  - Gilboʿa, Yaʿkov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18, Reel 2U)
  - Ziṿ, Shmeʿul, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - bar-Sever, ʾAvivah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - ʾEṭinger, ʿAmos, evidence, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - ʾEnden, ʾElishevʿa, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - Goldman, Maʾir (Maks), Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - Goldman, Miriam and Yehudah Gor, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - Gor, Yehudah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - Tsur, Hilel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 19, Reel 2U)
  - Shakhṭerman, ʾAvraham, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - HaLeṿi, Ḥayyim Shalom, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - ʾAnat, Dr. Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - ben-Ziṿ, ʾAvraham, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Ḥason, Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Ḥason, Śarah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Yelin, ʿUzi, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Yelin, Śarah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - ʿEyyifer, ʿEvriah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳuḳ, Hilel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 20, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳaniuḳ, Professor Yoram, evidences, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21, Reel 2U)
  - Israeli television, evidences, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 21, Reel 2U)
  - Perlman, Yosef, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22, Reel 2U)
  - HaLeṿi, Shmuʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳariv, ʾAvivah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22, Reel 2U)
  - Ḳaṭan, Yoʾev, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Siḳaʾ, Yaʿḳov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Naev, Daṿid, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Rozenblum, Dr. Hertsel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - ben-Ḥaruts(ḳy), ʾAriah, about, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Yungman, Shlomah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Meser, Yafah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - HaLeṿi, Shmuʾel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Yelin-Mor, Fridah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - ʾElḥanny, Reʾuven and Raḥel, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Groman, Yaʿḳov, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Ḳup, Yoneh, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Brozeh, Rut, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Tselniḳ, Yitsḥaḳ, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Svoraʾi, Masha, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Reṭosh, Jonatan, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Ḳelmos, Ḥanah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Piron, Ṭovah, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Mendel, Sidy, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 23, Reel 3U)
  - Ḳlaʿi, Ḥanukh, Circa 1970-circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24, Reel 3U)
  - Biographies, Undated (Box 3, Folder 25-26, Reel 3U)
  - Songbooks (Stern), Undated (Box 3, Folder 27-28, Reel 3U)
  - Documents
    - Explanatory material, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 29, Reel 3U)
    - 1-180, 1929-1984 (Box 4, Folder 30-39, Reel 3U)
    - 181-441, 1929-1984 (Box 4, Folder 40-50, Reel 4U)
    - 442-456, 1933-1984 (Box 5, Folder 51-53D, Reel 4U)
- Iraqi Jewish immigration files, 1949-1985; Series II
  Series II, Iraqi Jewish immigration files, contains over 500 documents collected by Nadel after he was asked to write a book on the mass emigration of Jews from Iraq to Israel in 1950-1951. The documents include interviews, printed materials, and copies of government records which chronicle Jewish life in Iraq, the history of illegal immigration in the 1940s, and the events which brought about the mass exodus.
  Nadel asserts that his collections of documents sheds light on a conspiracy in which the governments of Iraq, Israel, the United States, and Great Britain worked together to force the Jews of Iraq to immigrate to Israel. He further contends that leaders of the Zionist movement in Palestine and the new Israeli government attempted to create suspicions about "Zionist agents" among Iraqi Jews; that the United States government aided in efforts to transfer to Israel middle class Iraqi Jews, who formed a nucleus of the Iraqi Communist Party; and that the Israeli government secretly organized attacks on Iraqi Jewish businesses in order to scare Iraqi Jews into leaving the country.
  The documents are arranged in numerical order according to the arbitrary numbers assigned to them by Nadel. Nadel's sources included the files of the Jewish Agency which was responsible for the immigration of Iraqi Jews, and members of the Israeli secret service. His notes which explain the background for his research and describe the importance of individual documents are in folder 54. These notes also serve as an inventory to the series.
  Materials in this series are arranged in numerical order.
  - Documents
    - Explanatory material, Circa 1985 (Box 6, Folder 54, Reel 5U)
    - 1-275, 1949-1979 (Box 6, Folder 55-67, Reel 5U)
    - 276-370, 1950-1978 (Box 7, Folder 68-70, Reel 6U)
    - 371-516, 1950-1979 (Box 7, Folder 71-74, Reel 7U)
  - Appendix, 1977, undated (Box 7, Folder 75, Reel 7U)
- Other files, 1918-1985; Series III
  Series III, Other papers, is composed of correspondence, writings, printed material and other documents which relate to Nadel's father, Menahem Nadel, and others involved in early Zionist political groups. The papers also contain materials Nadel collected concerning Palestine under the Mandate and State of Israel, 1918-1985.
  The materials are arranged in folders as Nadel organized them. Within each folder in box 8, Nadel has included his own notes, in Hebrew, explaining the significance of individual items. Items within the folders have been arranged to insure proper long term storage and may not appear in exactly the same order as described by Nadel in his folder notes.